<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rongmon Bordoloi</title><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/</link><description>Recent content on Rongmon Bordoloi</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/fermi-bubbles/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/fermi-bubbles/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="the-fermi-bubbles"&gt;
 The Fermi Bubbles
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#the-fermi-bubbles"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/images/FB_map.jpg" alt="Fermi Bubble Map" style="max-width: 500px; height: auto;"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fermi Bubbles are the smoking gun of the Milky Way&amp;rsquo;s violent past—two colossal lobes of plasma extending 55,000 light-years above and below our Galactic Center. These structures reveal a cataclysmic explosion that erupted from the supermassive black hole at the galaxy&amp;rsquo;s heart, reshaping the entire halo of our galaxy. Through a &lt;a href="https://www.stsci.edu/~afox/group/fb.html" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;long-running observational program&lt;/a&gt;, we use Hubble Space Telescope UV spectroscopy combined with radio observations from the Green Bank Telescope to measure the age, energy, and momentum of this cosmic explosion—revealing the physical mechanism driving some of the most powerful feedback events in the universe. We have recently been awarded over 200 hours of Green Bank Telescope time (PI Bordoloi) to map the hidden population of neutral hydrogen gas entrained at high latitudes within the Fermi Bubbles, providing unprecedented constraints on the cold gas distribution and survival mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/galaxy-quenching/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/galaxy-quenching/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="how-galaxies-quench-star-formation"&gt;
 How Galaxies Quench Star Formation
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#how-galaxies-quench-star-formation"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Research Themes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/milky-way-evolution/" &gt;How do galaxies like the Milky Way become what they are?&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/mass-acquisition/" &gt;How do galaxies acquire their mass?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;
 Overview
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#overview"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most fundamental puzzles in astrophysics is understanding why galaxies stop forming stars. Massive galaxies in the Universe today are &amp;ldquo;red and dead&amp;rdquo;—they contain trillions of stars but have virtually ceased star formation. The mechanism driving this quenching is galactic outflows: powerful winds driven by star formation and active galactic nuclei that transport gas and metals far from galaxies. By studying these outflows across cosmic time, we reveal how feedback regulates galaxy evolution and sets the fundamental properties of the galaxy population we observe today.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/mass-acquisition/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/mass-acquisition/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="how-galaxies-acquire-their-mass"&gt;
 How Galaxies Acquire Their Mass
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#how-galaxies-acquire-their-mass"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Research Themes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/milky-way-evolution/" &gt;How do galaxies like the Milky Way become what they are?&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/galaxy-quenching/" &gt;How do galaxies quench star formation?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;
 Overview
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#overview"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galaxies do not exist in isolation—they are embedded in vast networks of gas and dark matter that extend far beyond their stars. To understand how galaxies grow from the cosmic dawn to the present day, we must study how they acquire mass from their surroundings and how they transform the intergalactic medium through feedback. Our research spans the full cosmic history, from nearby galaxies to the epoch of reionization, revealing &lt;strong&gt;how gas flows in and out of galaxies regulate their growth and transform the Universe itself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/milky-way-evolution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/milky-way-evolution/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="how-galaxies-like-the-milky-way-became-what-they-are"&gt;
 How Galaxies Like the Milky Way Became What They Are
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#how-galaxies-like-the-milky-way-became-what-they-are"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Research Themes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/galaxy-quenching/" &gt;How do galaxies quench star formation?&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/mass-acquisition/" &gt;How do galaxies acquire their mass?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;
 Overview
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#overview"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galaxies are shaped by the interplay between internal dynamics and external accretion over billions of years. To understand how the Milky Way and similar galaxies achieved their current structure, we must study the dynamical imprints of past feedback events and the circumgalactic medium at low redshifts. By examining nearby and low-redshift galaxies, we reconstruct their assembly histories and reveal how gravitational processes, star formation, and supermassive black hole activity have left lasting signatures on galactic structure and kinematics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Galactic Outflows</title><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/galactic-outflows/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/galactic-outflows/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="galactic-outflows"&gt;
 Galactic Outflows
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#galactic-outflows"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/images/M82_Chandra_HST_Spitzer_small.jpg" alt="M82"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galactic outflows are crucial in chemically enriching the circumgalactic medium as well as in regulating star-formation in a galaxy. The modern theory of galaxy evolution demands strong feedback processes that regulate the exchange of gas into and out of galaxies. Such processes are crucial in setting up the mass metallicity relation, the quenching of star-formation, and in explaining the mismatch between the galaxy stellar mass function and the dark matter halo mass function. Some of my recent work on this field are listed below.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>New observations with Integral Field Spectrographs</title><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/ifu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/ifu/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="new-observations-with-integral-field-spectrographs"&gt;
 New observations with Integral Field Spectrographs
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#new-observations-with-integral-field-spectrographs"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/images/IFU.jpg" alt="IFU"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Integral field spectrograph is a spectrograph equipped with an integral field unit (IFU). In this method, the light from each pixel of the detector is fed into a spectrograph, which generates a spectrum for each individual pixel. This muliplexing capability allows one to obtain spectra of every single pixel of an image simultaneously. This is a game changer in terms of how astropysical observations are carried out.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Observing with the James Webb Space Telescope</title><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/jwst/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/jwst/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="observing-with-the-james-webb-space-telescope"&gt;
 Observing with the James Webb Space Telescope
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#observing-with-the-james-webb-space-telescope"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/images/JWST1.jpg" alt="JWST"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.jwst.nasa.gov/" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)&lt;/a&gt; is NASA&amp;rsquo;s next generation flagship space telescope and is the successor of the &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/hubble/main/index.html" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Hubble Space telesocpe (HST)&lt;/a&gt;. JWST will have a 6.5m deployable primary mirror which is almost three times larger than HST&amp;rsquo;s primary mirror. This powerful telescope will observe primarily in near infra-red wavelength range and will have both imagers and spectrographs and will be an incredible tool to study of distant galaxies, including those seen at z &amp;gt; 10 when the first generations of stars lit up a dark Universe, and for cool objects such as forming stars and planetary systems. JWST was launched on &lt;a href="https://www.jwst.nasa.gov/" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;December 25, 2021&lt;/a&gt;. The image is an artist&amp;rsquo;s impression of the JWST deployed at the L2 point 1.5 million km from Earth [Credit NASA].&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Photometric Redshifts</title><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/photometric-redshifts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/photometric-redshifts/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="photometric-redshifts"&gt;
 Photometric Redshifts
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#photometric-redshifts"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/images/photoz.jpg" alt="Photo-z"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photometric redshifts are crude distance estimators to distant galaxies. In absence of spectroscopic information, photometric redshifts provide vital distance information for cosmological stidues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="photo-z-performance-for-precision-cosmology---ii-empirical-verification"&gt;
 Photo-z performance for precision cosmology - II. Empirical verification:
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#photo-z-performance-for-precision-cosmology---ii-empirical-verification"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://rongmonbordoloi.com/images/photoz2.jpg" alt="Photo-z 2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of future large-scale weak-lensing surveys will critically depend on the accurate estimation of photometric redshifts of very large samples of galaxies. This in turn depends on both the quality of the photometric data and the photo-z estimators. In a previous study, we focused primarily on the impact of photometric quality on photo-z estimates and on the development of novel techniques to construct the N(z) of tomographic bins at the high level of precision required for precision cosmology, as well as the correction of issues such as imprecise corrections for Galactic reddening. We used the same set of templates to generate the simulated photometry as were then used in the photo-z code, thereby removing any effects of &amp;rsquo;template error&amp;rsquo;. In this work we now include the effects of &amp;rsquo;template error&amp;rsquo; by generating simulated photometric data set from actual COSMOS photometry. We use the trick of simulating redder photometry of galaxies at higher redshifts by using a bluer set of passbands on low-z galaxies with known redshifts. We find that &amp;rsquo;template error&amp;rsquo; is a rather small factor in photo-z performance, at the photometric precision and filter complement expected for all-sky surveys. With only a small subset of training galaxies with spectroscopic redshifts, it is in principle possible to construct tomographic redshift bins whose mean redshift is known, from photo-z alone, to the required accuracy of |Δ&lt;z&gt;|≤ 0.002(1 +z). For more information see &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2012MNRAS.421.1671B/" class="external-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Bordoloi et al 2012.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Circumgalactic Medium</title><link>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/cgm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rongmonbordoloi.com/research/cgm/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="the-circumgalactic-medium"&gt;
 The Circumgalactic Medium
 &lt;a class="heading-link" href="#the-circumgalactic-medium"&gt;
 &lt;i class="fa-solid fa-link" aria-hidden="true" title="Link to heading"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;span class="sr-only"&gt;Link to heading&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CircumGalactic Medium (CGM), is losely defined as a region spanning a few hundred kiloparsecs from a galaxy that contains an extended reservoir of diffuse gas. Our recent understanding of galaxy evolution has dramatically changed with new understanding of how the circumgalactic medium influences star-formation in galaxies. The CGM is a major reservoir of baryons in a galaxy and is actively regulating galaxy evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>